[MUSIC PLAYING]
CARTER ZENKE: Well, hello, one
and all and welcome back to CS50's
Introduction to Databases with SQL.
My name is Carter Zenke.
And last we left off, we
learned all about querying--
how to ask questions of
data in a single table.
Today, though, we'll
take one step forward,
and we'll have databases that have
not just one table inside of them
but, actually, multiple
tables-- tables for authors,
tables for books, and
for publishers, and so
on-- to represent all of these people
who are part of the book industry.
And you, too, can apply these
same skills for whatever
you want to represent as well.
So let's pick up where we left off,
which was with this database of books.
And I'll come back to
my computer over here.
And if you recall, we
had this data set that
was the books that were longlisted
for the International Booker Prize.
To be longlisted means to be nominated
for some prize in a given year.
And the international Booker Prize
is awarded every year to one book,
but 13 are nominated.
So in this data set, we have
13 books the past five years
that were nominated for this prize.
Now, I'll go ahead and open
up this database once more.
And if you remember, we used this
command last time to open this data
set-- sqlite3 space the file name,
where our file name was longlist.db.
And this is one example of our
database management system--
this one called SQLite, and this one
being the third version of SQLite.
So let's re-open this database and let
me show you what we have now in store.
I'll type sqlite--
whoops, I'll type sqlite--
sqlite3 and then longlist.db.
And I'll hit Enter.
Now, my prompt changes.
I no longer have this dollar sign.
I now have the SQLite prompt.
And here's what we saw last time--
I could write my SQL queries.
Well, before we start, let's see
the changes to this database.
So if I want to get a feel
for the tables that are inside
of this database, I can use a command--
this one called .tables.
Notice this is not a SQL keyword.
This is a command particular
to SQLite to show me
what tables are inside this database.
So I'll type enter here.
And now I see I have
more than one table.
I have a table for authors, a table for
books, for publishers, and even more.
And now that we're working with
not just one table but multiple,
we're actually moving into this
idea of a relational database.
So no longer do we have a database
with only one table inside of it.
We now have multiple.
And these tables, presumably, have
some kind of relationship among them.
You could think, for instance,
of an author writing a book,
or a publisher publishing a book, or
even a translator translating a book.
So we'll have these tables and
these relationships among them.
So let's look at one example of this
kind of relationship among tables.
I could have a table
of authors and a table
of books-- this simplified for
now to one column in every table.
Well, with my authors
table, I have names.
In my books table, I have titles.
And we seem to be moving
in the right direction.
I could store more information
about authors and books.
But I've also created some problem.
Like, how do I know, now,
who wrote which book?
Like, earlier, we saw that, maybe,
Eva is right next to Boulder
in a single table for authors and books.
And we know that Eva
wrote Boulder that way.
But now, if I look at authors, I only
see Eva and no information about books.
So we seem to have this problem here.
Well, one solution might be
something like the honor system.
I'm honest.
And, presumably, so are you.
We could say that. well,
maybe the first row in authors
will always correspond to
the first row in books.
So we always know Eva wrote Boulder
because Eva's first in the authors
table and Boulder is
first in the books table.
Similarly, let's say Han wrote The White
Book because Han is in the second row
and The White Book is in
the second row in books.
But I have to imagine, as good as I
am at being honest and transparent,
maybe I make a mistake.
Maybe I add a row to
books but not to authors.
Or maybe I add a row to
authors and not to books.
I could change data and not update
it to adhere to that standard.
So let's actually take a step back and
maybe think, well, is it better, then,
to have this kind of
situation, where we did
have one table with authors and books?
It might be.
But let's think.
This could work for a while.
But let's say Olga is a prolific author.
They like to write not
just one book but two.
They wrote not just Flights
but also The Books of Jacob.
Well, let's say Olga writes
another book or another one too.
What might be the problem
with this arrangement now?
And feel free to raise your
hand, too, with your ideas.
Well, I might run into
some issues here if we only
have one table of authors and books.
SPEAKER: There is some
redundancy, some repetition.
CARTER ZENKE: Yeah, good idea.
So you might notice there's
some redundancy here.
Olga is in here twice, which is
maybe OK if Olga wrote two books.
But, again, let's say Olga
wrote three, or four, or five.
Olga will be in here that many times.
And so we could probably
do a bit better than this.
And let's actually
just say this is going
to be the most efficient idea for us.
Let's go back to these
multiple tables here
and think about how we could relate
these two tables, one to the other.
Now before we get into the details
of how we might do this technically,
let's think about the
kinds of relationships
we could have between authors and books.
Well, maybe, in our world, we have
one author that writes one book.
And maybe we could say every
author only writes one book.
And, similarly, one book is
always written by one author.
This could be true for some
books and some authors.
But, arguably, it's not
the best assumption, right?
We probably have authors writing
more than one book or books
being written by more than one author.
So as it stands now, we could
call this kind of relationship
a one-to-one relationship.
If this is our idea of authors and
books, one author writes one book,
and one book is written by one author.
This is a one-to-one relationship.
Well, as we know, authors
can write more than one book.
Olga, for example, didn't
write just Flights.
They also wrote another book.
And so we could say, well, Olga
wrote not just this book up top.
They also wrote this book down below.
And now we're moving from a
one-to-one relationship to what we'll
call a one-to-many relationship.
There are many books that
one author could write.
But, of course, is this
the full picture, too?
Some books are only
written by one author.
But, presumably, some books are
written by multiple authors.
So we need to enhance
our picture even further.
Let's try that.
Let me add another
author into the mix here.
This author wrote this book
along with Olga, let's say.
So notice how here we have one
author writing more than one book,
and we also have one book being
written by more than one author.
Well, this is called a
many-to-many relationship.
And it's called that because
we have many books that
can be written by many authors.
So these, in general, are
the kinds of relationships
we'll have amongst our tables in a
relational database-- one-to-one,
one-to-many, and many-to-many.
Now, thankfully, there
are some tools we can
use to visualize these
kinds of relationships.
We have at our disposal something
called an Entity Relationship
Diagram, something a bit like this.
It's also called an
ER diagram for short.
And let me propose, just for now, that
this is the diagram for our database.
We have authors, and publishers,
and translators, books, and ratings.
These are our entities in our database,
the things we're trying to represent.
Now, you'll notice, though, that there's
something more than just these boxes
that have author, publisher,
translator, and so on.
There are all these lines among them.
And they have verbs like wrote,
and published, and translated.
And maybe that makes sense to you.
But at first glance,
there's one line here
that has three lines coming off
of it, one line going across.
This one has a circle on it.
What does all that mean?
This is kind of confusing
at first glance.
Well, this actually has some order
to it, some rules that we can use.
And let me show you
what those rules are.
So here, we have what's
called a crow's foot notation,
a way of trying to represent
one-to-one, one-to-many,
or many-to-many relationships using
just lines and, in some cases, circles.
So here, if you ever see this
line with a circle on it,
you could think of zero.
This doesn't have to have
anything related to it.
You could think of this one with
a bar going perpendicular as one.
Something with this arrow has
to have at least one thing that
relates to it in some other table.
And this one down below, the one
that looks like a crow's foot-- well,
this one means that some
entity has many that could
be related to it in some other table.
So let's try this with an example.
Here we have, again, our
authors and our books.
And here we can say that
an author wrote one book.
We read this left to right in this case.
One author can have one
book associated with them.
We know it's one because we see
this bar over our line here.
Now we know, too, that
books, at least in our world,
could be written by one author.
They must be written
by at least one author.
So let's try this.
I'll include that arrow
on the other side too.
And I'll read this right to left.
A book has to have at least one author.
Now, I could add in more symbols too.
We know that books could
have more than one author
and an author could
write more than one book.
So let's try enhancing
our diagram even further.
I could say-- adding in these crow's
foot notation with the multiple lines
here, now I could read it like this--
an author, going from left to
right, can write at least one book,
but they could write many books.
They could write one or many books.
And, similarly, a book could be
written by at least one author
but, certainly, also multiple too.
So this is one example of an
ER diagram for our database.
And, hopefully, now you can see a
bit more of this making sense to you.
So we see that authors,
here, could write many books.
A book could be written by many authors.
Books, actually, don't
need to have a translator.
They could have zero to many
translators for their book here.
But, in general, a
translator should write--
or should translate at least one
book or possibly many of them too.
So let me pause here and
ask, what questions do you
have on these table
relationships and these diagrams
that we call ER Entity
Relationship Diagrams?
SPEAKER: Yeah, so, Carter, I want
to ask that for any given database,
how can we predetermine whether how
the relationship between the tables
are going to be?
Because here we know that the author
has some relationship to the books.
But how can we determine
whether those relationships
are existent in the first place?
CARTER ZENKE: A great question.
If we have some database, how
do we know the relationships
among those entities or those
things that are stored inside of it?
Well, part of this is really up to you.
When you're designing a database--
as we'll see in a future week of this
course--
you have decisions to make.
Do you want an author to
be able to write only one
book or multiple, for instance?
Often, when I design a database,
I might write a diagram like this
so I could show this to somebody
else who can know what tables I have
and how they are related to one another.
So if you're designing,
you have the choice.
But if you're taking a
database from someone else,
you could ask for a diagram
like this that could show you
those relationships among those tables.
Let's see, what other
questions do we have
too on these tables and
their relationships?
SPEAKER: How do we
determine that relationship?
I mean, we know that it exists.
But how we assign which author
wrote which book or multiple books,
or which book were
written by what authors?
CARTER ZENKE: Yeah, a great question.
So how do we try to assign, then,
these relationships, perhaps,
in our database?
Look, we know that an author
could write multiple books,
but how do we represent that
in our table, let's say.
Well for this, let me just transition to
the next part of what we'll talk about,
which is going to be this idea of a key.
So keys are this fundamental
idea in databases
that can help us relate
tables one to the other.
And for this, let's actually do a bit
of an example, a bit of a roleplay here.
So I will be your librarian today.
And let's say that you're
looking for a book.
This one is called The Birthday Party.
And I say, OK, I'll find you this book.
I'll go to my computer here, and I will
try to find you The Birthday Party.
Here, though, I have two options.
I seem to have The Birthday
Party by Wendy Dranfield,
and The Birthday Party
by Laurent Mauvignier.
So let me ask you-- if we're
on the phone, perhaps--
which one do you want?
I'm hearing , feel free to vote, which
book should we search for-- the one
by Wendy or the one by Laurent?
I'm hearing, maybe, going for Laurent.
So let's try Laurent over here.
We'll search for the one by Laurent.
So The Birthday Party
by Laurent Mauvignier.
OK, OK, let me find you that book.
But-- well, now there's still
two books I could choose from.
Do you want it in
hardcover or paperback?
And so I could ask you, again,
well, which one do you want?
Do you want it in
hardcover or paperback?
And, again, feel free to vote--
which book do you want?
OK, I'm hearing-- we're going
for, I think, closer to paperback.
Let's try that one.
So we'll search for The Birthday Party
by Laurent Mauvignier in paperback.
And [SIGHS] there are still two of them.
Which one do you want?
We have first edition, and
we have second edition.
So I would ask you, again,
which book do you really want?
And you could keep voting here, but for
the sake of just keeping this going,
let's pause here and think
of a better way to do this.
My life, as a librarian,
would be much easier
if you had given me a simple number.
This number is called an ISBN.
And it turns out that every book has
a unique identifier called an ISBN.
Now, what is an ISBN really?
Well, if it's the case that
every book has a unique ISBN,
and I can only find one
book if I have an ISBN,
this is what we call in
database terms a primary key--
something that is going to be
unique for our book or for any item
that we have in our table.
Now, here's one example of an ISBN.
Notice how we have a 978-1-8042--
whatever it is.
We could use this to uniquely
identify, at least, our books.
But we could extract this away and
use this in more than one place--
not just for books but for publishers,
for translators, for authors as well,
giving them each some id that
uniquely identifies them.
So here's one example of our table.
Let's say that I have a table of books.
And I used to only have titles.
But now, I actually
have more than a title.
I have an ISBN to uniquely
identify each of these books.
And this is handy for me if
I wanted to look up some book
and know exactly which
one I was talking about.
Now these are all fine
and good in tables.
They're very helpful.
But we could do a little more with them.
We could get to this question
of, how do we actually
relate these tables together?
We could use these
primary keys for that.
Now, a primary key becomes
useful for that kind of work
when we treat it as a
foreign key, let's call it.
Well, what is a foreign key?
Well, a foreign key is simply
taking a primary key from one table
and including it in the
column of some other table.
So here we have, in the ratings
table, the ISBN column still.
This is the primary key
for the books table.
But now notice how it's
inside the ratings table.
This is now a foreign key because
it is outside of this books table
and inside the ratings table.
And what could I do with this?
Well, I now see if I want to find
all of the individual users ratings
for Boulder, I could look--
what is the ISBN of Boulder
and, then which ratings correspond
to that ISBN in some other table?
So this is an example of
how we could represent
these one-to-many relationships.
I have, here, a table that has
an ISBN, or a list of ISBNs,
and I have another
table that can tell me
which ratings correspond to this ISBN,
this primary key in this other table
here.
Well, that solves one picture here.
How I can represent these
one-to-many relationships?
But we could also think about how we do
the many-to-many relationships as well.
And for this, we'll
need to think about how
we can improve our primary key here.
So let me ask.
This is an ISBN.
But if I want to put this
inside of a computer, like,
over and over and over
again as a primary key--
it's the unique identifier--
what problems do you think I
might run into here, if any?
What problems would I get by
using this ISBN as my primary key?
SPEAKER: You would,
like, run out of memory.
CARTER ZENKE: Run out of
memory-- it's a good guess.
If I had a lot of ISBNs--
so, let's say I had not just 78 books,
but I had literally millions of books,
this is a lot of data to store.
If you treated each of these
as an individual character,
that's about 1 byte,
8 bits per character.
That's, let's say, 13 plus four dashes--
17 bytes per ISBN, which takes
up a lot, a lot of space.
So what if I, instead, said, I'll
remove the dashes like we did before.
And I'll treat it as a number.
Well, in that case, I
might also have a problem.
Let's say an ISBN begins with 0.
And if I convert that to a
number, I'll lose that beginning 0
because it doesn't really mean anything
in the context of being a number.
And now I've lost my unique identifier.
So we could improve this even further.
And we can actually construct
our very own primary key.
This one, let's just say, will
be called 1 for this book.
And some other book, we could call
it 2, some other book, maybe, 3.
And it doesn't quite
matter what number we
choose so long as this number uniquely
identifies the book that we choose
and we don't use that number
for any other book as well.
So let's actually rethink this
relationship of one-to-many here.
Let's not just use ISBN.
This is a lot of space to
use, to someone point earlier.
Let's go ahead and use the id.
Let's make our own primary
key in our books table
and use that as the
foreign key in ratings.
So we freed up a good
amount of space here.
And notice, too, that maybe Boulder
has the primary key, the id of 1.
The White Book has the id of 74.
Well, does it matter
if it's 1, 2, 3, or 4?
It doesn't as long as 74 uniquely
identifies The White Book, we're OK.
So here we have an example
of a one-to-many relationship
but now improved.
And with this improvement, we could then
think about many-to-many relationships
as well.
I could take the same idea and use
it to relate authors and books.
So let's think about this
relationship now here too.
Let's say I have a table of
authors and a table of books.
And, notably, each has a primary key.
So I could use that primary
key for authors and for books,
and, perhaps, put it in some new table.
This one, let's say, is called authored.
And I'll have one column for
author_id and one column for book_id.
And based on the
context clues here, what
might it mean if I looked
at the author table
and saw 23 next to 1, where
23 is in the author_id column
and 1 is in the book_id column?
Feel free to raise your hand.
What would it mean for me to see
those two numbers next to each other?
SPEAKER: Yeah, it would
mean that the author that
is read that has the id of
23 has authored the book 1.
CARTER ZENKE: Yeah, a
great instinct here.
So if I look at author_id, I see 23.
Well, I could consider that maybe
the author with the id of 23
wrote the book with the id of 1.
And I'll concede there's
some extra work here.
I have to figure out, now, who
has this author idea of 23.
Well, it turns out if I look in
the author's table, it's Eva.
Similarly, for the
book_id, I now have to go
through the process of figuring
out, OK, well the book_id is 1.
What, then, is the book title?
And I'll look for that in
my books table over here.
So it brings in a bit more work for me.
But, ultimately, I think
we've solved our problem
from the very beginning of lecture,
trying to relate authors and books.
We can now do that using both
primary keys and foreign keys.
So, let me ask, then, what
questions do we have on these keys
and how to use them?
SPEAKER: So if the i--
can the id of the author
and the book_id be the same?
For example, can there be an
author_id of 1 and a book_id of 1,
or will they be mixed together?
CARTER ZENKE: A really good
question and good thinking here.
So let's consider that, maybe,
an author_id matches a book's id.
Both authors-- both the author
and the book have this id of 1.
That's actually, I would say, OK in our
case because we know that at least 1
refers to authors and 1 refers to books.
And as we'll see in future lectures,
too, when I make this join table,
also called a joint table or a
junction table, an associative entity,
I could claim that this column
called author_id references
the primary key column in authors
and that primary key only.
I could do the same
thing for the book side.
I could say the numbers in here
reference the primary keys in the books
table and those ids only.
So I could actually have authors
and books with the same id
so long as my tables know
that if I have this column,
I'm looking for author_ids; this
column, I'm looking for book_ids.
Great question.
Let's go to one more here.
SPEAKER: I was wondering--
it feels like having
more and more tables because once you
do this on a big scale, it adds up.
It would use up a lot of space as well.
How does it-- how do you deal with
the tediousness of it adding up?
CARTER ZENKE: Yeah,
a good question here.
So if we had a lot of these kinds of
tables, wouldn't that take more space?
And I think your answer--
the answer to that question is it
would, but we do gain some things
by being able to do it this way.
So, for example, let me go back
to my authors and books table.
In our database, we'll see we have not
just author names, but also the year
they were born, the
city they were born in,
the place that they were living
in certain periods of their life,
and so on.
So we could have much more
information in these tables
that we couldn't store
as one table earlier
because of all these redundancies
we saw a little bit earlier.
So, I think, although this might
take up a little more space,
use a little more
tables, we can get around
that-- as we'll see later on-- with
some creativeness with our queries,
too, to address that downside but a good
question, a good thought for trade-offs
here.
Let's go to one more here.
SPEAKER: So my question is
that can the id be updated?
And if so, does it automatically
get updated in the one
that has both the ids together?
CARTER ZENKE: Yeah, good question.
So maybe we want to change
the id of some book or author.
Could we do that?
I would say you could, but
it's kind of a dangerous game.
If I changed Eva from
23, let's say, to--
so we change it to 27, well, I
could get Eva confused with Gauz.
And I need to be doubly sure that when
I'm changing these ids, I'm making sure
that I'm not making an id nonunique.
I'm not making it an id that
somebody else already has.
And so for that reason,
we very rarely change ids.
In fact, we tend to
just abstract them away.
So we don't actually know the
id of any particular author
or the id of any particular book.
We just use them in our queries,
as we'll see in just a moment.
So wonderful questions here.
What we'll do is take a very
short break and come back
to see how we can use these same tools
of keys to not just relate tables,
but to query them, too, and find answers
to our questions across these tables.
We'll be back in just a minute.
Well, we're back.
And what we saw before was how
to relate our tables using keys.
We saw that we could have tables
of authors, and translators,
and books related to each other
using primary keys and foreign keys.
So what we'll do now
is figure out how we
can query these tables using different
techniques that, in this case,
might actually use primary keys and
foreign keys within those same queries.
Now one technique we could use
is this one called subqueries,
also called nested queries,
too, that basically
put one SQL query inside of another.
And they're useful in
a few different cases.
But let's say I have one case
of a one-to-many relationship.
Maybe I have publishers that are
publishing many books, for instance.
Well, I could use subqueries
to help me answer questions
about these kinds of
relationships in my table.
To make it more concrete, let's
say I have a table of books,
and I want to figure
out which of these books
were published by Fitzcarraldo Editions,
my favorite publisher, let's say.
What's the problem here?
I want to find the books published
by Fitzcarraldo Editions,
but what am I missing?
Feel free to raise your hand and answer.
SPEAKER: Well, we don't have the name
of the publisher in the same table.
And we haven't made the
relationship with the other table
to know the name of publisher.
CARTER ZENKE: Yeah, good observation.
So I want to find the books that are
published by Fitzcarraldo Editions.
And, as you noted, well,
there's no publisher name.
There's just the id.
So I need to have some way of
knowing what these ids correspond to.
And thankfully, I do have
a way of knowing that.
I have a table called publishers.
And this has a column called id
and a column called publisher.
And what do I notice?
Well, I notice that Fitzcarraldo
Editions has the id of 5.
So I could probably solve this problem.
But let me ask again, what queries
might I need to answer this question?
There are two queries that I need
to do to answer the question of,
which books were published
by Fitzcarraldo Editions?
What two queries are they?
SPEAKER: I think it's SELECT and WHERE.
Did you mean keywords or queries?
CARTER ZENKE: Yeah, so
keywords would be great.
So I need to have some
kind of SELECT involved.
I need to probably select something from
publishers and something from books.
So could I ask you, what would
I select from publishers,
and what would I select from books then?
Let's take either another
hand or following up here.
SPEAKER: OK, so we would
take the publisher,
so select publisher_id from
, WHERE publisher equals,
the publisher name we're looking for.
And then we would nest this
query inside the other one
so we can find the name of the
book published by this publisher,
since we found the id.
CARTER ZENKE: Yeah,
some good ideas here.
And let me propose to do it
a bit visually here first.
So I want to figure out, first, what
is the id of Fitzcarraldo Editions?
Well, I could write
a query to find that.
And I'll, say, get back 5
for Fitzcarraldo Editions.
Well, that's one step.
But my next step is then to say,
what books fit that publisher_id?
So I'll write another
query, this one to determine
which titles have a publisher_id of 5.
And I'll get back, let's say,
Minor Detail and Paradais.
So let's make this more concrete, as
you were doing yourself, Jean Paul.
And let's write these queries out.
Let's say I have this
first one to determine what
is the id of Fitzcarraldo Editions.
I could say SELECT "id"
FROM "publishers" WHERE
the publisher is Fitzcarraldo Editions.
And I'll get back from
this query the number 5.
Well, I could use that
number in my next query.
If we saw visually
here, I could then say,
SELECT "title" FROM "books"
WHERE "publisher_id" = 5.
And I would get, then,
back many titles here.
But here's another question.
Why is this not very well-designed?
At least, in the query I have here?
What could I improve about it?
Or what kind of smells
wrong about it for you?
SPEAKER: They are not connected.
CARTER ZENKE: Yeah, so, Jean-Paul, as
you said, too, they're not connected.
And here I have this id of 5.
But I don't want to
remember this number.
I don't want to have to keep it in my
mind and use it later on in my queries.
I, ideally, could use some other
query to find this number for me
more dynamically.
And so SQL supports this
idea of writing a subquery--
a query within a query.
For example, I'll take this, and I'll
convert it to the query we had before.
I'll SELECT "title" FROM "books" WHERE
"publisher_id" is equal to, well,
the result of this query here.
And notice how I have parentheses.
This means the query furthest inside
the parentheses will be run first.
So first, this query is run.
I get back 5.
Then I could finish out my query
and say, SELECT "title" FROM "books"
WHERE "publisher_id" is equal to 5.
So let me pause here before we do
some practice in our SQLite terminal.
What questions do we have on
these kinds of subqueries so far?
SPEAKER: I was wondering what would
happen with those records that
don't match in the subquery?
CARTER ZENKE: Yeah, good question.
So if the id doesn't match--
is that what you're asking?
Yeah, I'm going to guess.
So if the id doesn't match--
that's a good question.
So we can treat it as we
would a regular old SQL query
that we learned about in last week.
So we said SELECT "title" FROM "books"
WHERE "publisher_id" is equal to,
let's say, some value.
And we'll then filter out all of those
that don't have that particular value.
So if we have a
publisher_id of 6 or of 3,
those won't be included
anymore because we said
WHERE "publisher_id" is equal to 5.
And now looking at this
query, too, well, let's say,
I might write SELECT "id" FROM
"publishers" WHERE "publisher"
is or equal to 'Fitzcarraldo Editions'.
Maybe that publisher doesn't exist.
There's no publisher with that name.
Well, in that case, this
query would return nothing.
And therefore, the next query
would also return nothing.
So we have queries dependent on the
results of the other queries here.
So let's actually try this
using our SQLite terminal
to get a better feel for what we
can do with this kind of structure
for our queries.
I'll go back to my computer.
And I'll hop into my SQLite environment.
Let's say here I want
to do a similar query,
but I want to find those books
that were published by MacLehose
Editions-- or MacLehose Press, rather.
So let me try to attempt this
one-by-one going one step of the way,
and then finally combining my queries
into one I could use more dynamically.
So to our point earlier, we have to
first find the id of MacLehose Press.
Let me try to find that.
I'll say SELECT "id" FROM "publisher"
where the publisher is equal to none
other than 'MacLehose Press,' like
this, and my quotes semicolon hit Enter.
And hopefully-- oop--
I will see--
I'll see an error.
And based on this error--
let me ask our group here--
what did I do wrong?
SPEAKER: Judging by the error, I think
you just mistyped the table name.
CARTER ZENKE: Yeah, so I
probably mistyped the table name.
And we could probably parse this
if I look at the error itself.
So it says "Parse
error-- no such table--
publisher."
And that's true.
There is no table called publisher.
So let me fix this and run it again.
I'll say SELECT "id" FROM
the "publishers" table--
plural-- and we'll say
WHERE the "publisher"
is equal to 'MacLehose
Press,' like this.
And I'll hit a semicolon here.
And now fingers crossed,
this should work.
I do see an id of 12.
OK, So MacLehose Press-- the id is 12.
Now I want to find the books
that were published by this id.
So let me go to my book table.
I will say SELECT "title"
FROM "books", in this case,
WHERE the publisher id is equal to
12, as we saw before, semicolon.
Now I'll hit Enter.
And I'll see these are the books
that MacLehose Press has published.
But, again, as we saw
before, I could improve this.
I could make this better, more
dynamic, by nesting my queries--
having a subquery, a
query inside of a query.
So let's redo this.
I'll start at the end, essentially.
I'll say SELECT "title"
from my book table
where the publisher id
is or is equal to what?
Well, let's say I don't know it's 12.
I have to write another query here.
So to do that, I could
open up some parentheses--
is equal to a parentheses.
And then I'll hit Enter
to continue my query.
I'll indent four spaces--
space, space, space, space--
just a style convention
to keep things clean for me to show this
query is inside of this other query.
What I'll then do is
finish out this query.
I want to SELECT the "id" FROM
the publisher's table WHERE--
let me just indent again--
WHERE the "publisher" is equal to--
not Fitzcarraldo Editions-- is
equal to MacLehose Press, end quote.
And now, let me close my parentheses.
I have an open one here that I should
close to show this subquery is done.
I'll hit Enter, close my parentheses,
and now my entire query is done.
I can hit semicolon, hit Enter again.
And now I'll see the very
same results but more dynamic.
No longer do I have to hardcode the id.
I can make it more
dynamic, and I can actually
find it using my very own query here.
Let's try a different context too.
Maybe I want to find all of the
ratings for this book called
In Memory of Memory.
Well, maybe I'll try it step-by-step.
And what I'll first do is try to
find the id for In Memory of Memory.
I'll say SELECT "id" FROM--
let's go from the books table--
and let's say WHERE the
title is In Memory of Memory,
end quote, semicolon, hit Enter.
And we'll see 33.
So this book has the id 33.
OK, let's now look in our
ratings table for this id.
I'll say SELECT-- let's
go for SELECT "rating"
FROM my ratings table WHERE
the "book_id" is equal to 33,
I believe it was.
So now I'll hit Enter.
And now I should see all of
the ratings for this book.
And there are quite a
few that people have
left on this book-- on
the Goodreads website.
So let me again try to improve this
and make it just a little bit better.
I'll be more dynamic about it
and try to nest these queries.
I'll say SELECT "rating" FROM "ratings".
We'll start at the beginning.
We ultimately want ratings.
Well, I want those ratings WHERE the
"book_id" is equal to some number,
but I don't know what number yet.
So I have to write my own nested query.
I'll create a parentheses
like this, Enter.
I'll indent four spaces--
space, space, space, space.
And then I'll say I want to
find the "id" FROM the "books"
table WHERE this "title" is
equal to 'In Memory of Memory'.
And that is my subquery now.
So I'll close this out.
I'll hit Enter, close my parentheses.
Now I have a semicolon and hit Enter.
And I see those very same ratings.
Well, I could probably not get
back the individual ratings.
I want to kind of
average them over time.
So let's try that too.
I'll say the same thing.
SELECT "rating" FROM
"ratings", but now, no longer
do I want to select all the ratings.
I want to average them.
So I'll say SELECT the average
"rating" of this book FROM "ratings".
And now, let me go back
over to my nested query.
And I will hit Enter again.
And I will hit the up arrow to get
back access to my earlier parts
of my SQLite environment.
I'll hit Enter here,
close it out, semicolon.
And now I should see the
average rating for this book.
OK, so this is very handy for us.
We're able to kind of
replicate those queries
we would have done with a single
table but now using subqueries.
And so far, we've seen this working
for a relationship that is one-to-many.
We could also use subqueries
with many-to-many relationships,
these tables that have
many items over here
and many items over there
that relate in some way.
Let's try it, let's say,
with authors and books.
And I want to figure out,
let's say, which author
wrote Flights-- which
author wrote Flights.
So let me ask, what should
I figure out along the way
to get to the author who wrote Flights?
Could you walk me through what I
might need to know for that query,
SPEAKER: You need to know id
of author and of that book.
And based on that relation, you have
to join all three tables together.
CARTER ZENKE: Yeah, I have to know ids.
And I have to kind of walk across
the three tables, as you're saying.
So let's go back to our tables.
And I want to know, who wrote Flights?
Well, a good place to
start, to your point,
is to say, let's start at
Flights and find the id.
Well, the id of this seems to be 78.
Let me then look in our author table.
And let me try to find the author
id that corresponds with 78.
Well, I find 78 here.
What's next to it?
Well, 58-- so the author
id who wrote Flights is 58.
Well, who is 58?
I'll look in the author's table, and
I'll see this is none other than Olga.
So let's walk through trying
to make this query happen
but now using SQL keywords.
I'll start first with trying
to find the id of Flight.
So I'll SELECT the "id"
FROM the "books" table WHERE
the "title" is equal to 'Flights".
That's fair enough.
Now, I could nest this query--
put it inside another
query to find the author
id of the person who wrote Flights.
I'll do it a bit like this.
I'll SELECT "author_id" FROM
"authored" WHERE the "book_id"
is equal to my prior query, SELECT
"id" FROM "flights" WHERE "title"
is equal to-- or From "books" WHERE
"title" is equal to 'Flights'.
And now I could go one step further.
I could say I want to find the name
of the person who has this author_id.
Let me nest again.
Let me put this query--
SELECT "name" FROM "authors" WHERE
"id" = and put all the rest of it
inside of the nested query here.
So to be clear, I'll start from
the middle, find the id of Flights.
Then, I'll find the
author_id for that book_id.
And then I'll find the name of
the author who wrote that book.
OK, so a good number of
steps here, but let's
try it out ourselves
in our SQLite terminal.
I'll come back to my computer.
And here, maybe I want to
find all of those books--
or maybe not all of those books.
I want to find the author
of a particular book you
might be familiar with called The
Birthday Party from our librarian
conversation a little earlier.
Let me say, I want to first find
the id of The Birthday Party.
I'll say SELECT "id" FROM
"books" WHERE "title"
is equal to 'The Birthday Party'; Enter.
Now, the id is 8.
Let me keep that in mind.
And, actually, I don't
quite need to know this.
Let me try to nest this
query inside some other query
to keep going towards my goal of finding
the author of The Birthday Party.
So the next thing to figure out, as we
saw before, is finding the author_id.
I'll say SELECT, let's say, the
"author_id" from the "authored" table--
that table of authors
who have written books.
And I'll say WHERE the "book_id" is
none other than the one I got back
from this prior query.
Let me indent and say SELECT
"id" FROM "books" WHERE "title"
is equal to 'The Birthday Party'--
not a semicolon yet--
end my parentheses,
semicolon, hit Enter.
And now I see 44.
So we're getting there.
But now I have to figure out who has
the id of 44 in my author's table.
Well, let's keep going.
Let's clear our terminal
using Control-L.
And I will then say SELECT the
"name" from the "authors" table.
We're going to start
at the begi-- or we're
going to-- yeah, start at the beginning,
the place we want to actually get to.
Then I'll say WHERE
the "id" of that author
is equal to the result of this query--
what is the author_id associated
with the book I want to find.
So I'll SELECT "author_id"
FROM "authored",
and I'll say WHERE the "book_id"
is equal to another subquery.
Here I'll indent four
times and four again.
Now I'm nesting twice, right?
So I'll then say SELECT
"id" FROM "books",
and I'll hit Enter just to kind of
keep me on some good style here.
I'll indent eight times total.
And then I'll say WHERE--
WHERE-- let me just make sure
I'm doing the right thing--
WHERE the "title" is
'The Birthday Party'.
That was a lot.
Now we'll close out our queries.
I'll hit Enter, space, space, space
again, semicolon-- or parentheses,
Enter again, parentheses, semicolon,
and, hopefully, after all this typing,
we'll get back what we want.
We see our friend Laurent Mauvignier.
So this is an example of
trying to find the author who
wrote a particular book, although
it's a bit long-winded using
these kinds of subqueries.
So let me pose questions, then.
We've seen how to use these subqueries
for one-to-many relationships
and, also, many-to-many.
What questions do you have
about how to use these queries?
SPEAKER: I remember you talking
about books of the same name,
and how they can have different
versions, and et cetera.
How would you get the id
for the different versions
if they are titled the
same, as I'm guessing
you wouldn't set up a
foreign key to a title
because they would be the primary.
Or is it done differently?
CARTER ZENKE: A good question here.
So you could imagine a database that
has more than one edition of a book
inside of it.
Like maybe I have two editions
of The Birthday Party,
or the hardcover and the paperback
and all these other editions.
Well, in that case, what I
might do is try to-- actually,
this is a good segue.
I might have multiple ids
that I'm searching for.
Now let's say I don't care if it's
the hardcover or paperback version.
Well, I could look for
the id of 55 and 56
and try to find the
author of both of those.
So let's, actually, keep going here.
Let me show you a new keyword to
use for those kinds of questions
if you don't mind.
Let me come back to my computer.
And let's introduce
this new keyword that
can help us find the author of
not just one book but, perhaps,
multiple books, or different
versions of the same book.
Let me introduce this one.
This one is called IN--
very simple, just I-N. And I can
use IN to say, well, maybe some key
or some column is IN some set
of values, not just equal to 1,
but IN some set of values.
So let's see an example here.
We're back at our authors,
books, and authored tables.
And maybe I want to find the books
written by these two authors, Gauz
and Olga.
Well, I could select their ids.
I could, say, get back 27 and 58.
Now I have two ids.
So I could look in author.
And I could say, give me
back all of the book ids
that have an author_id of 27 and 58.
I'll look here.
And I'll get back both 4 and 78.
So notice how earlier
I was asking, show me
the book ids where author_id
is equal to some single value.
Here, I'm asking find me the
book ids where book_id has--
or the author_id is in
some set of values--
more than one now.
And, similarly, let me
look at my books table.
Let me say, OK, I want to find
the titles for these books.
Well, I'll find the titles that
have book ids in this set of ids--
4 and 78.
So let's see this in
action in our SQL terminal.
I'll come back over here.
And I'll write this query
to find all of the books
by a particular author
named Fernanda Melchor.
So I go back to my terminal.
And Fernanda is more prolific than most.
She's written, actually,
two books that are
on the longlist for the Booker Prize.
So I'll say SELECT "id" FROM "authors"
WHERE the "name" is equal to Fernanda--
'Fernanda Melchor', semicolon.
And this now is Fernanda's id--
24.
Let me find the ids of books
that Fernanda has written.
I will now say SELECT "book_id"--
if I can type--
SELECT "book_id" FROM
the "authored" table
WHERE the "author_id" is equal
to the result of this query--
1, 2, 3, 4 spaces here.
And I'll say SELECT "id" FROM
"authors" WHERE the "name"
is equal to 'Fernanda Melchor',
parentheses, semicolon.
And I'll hit Enter.
And I'll get back not
one book id, but two.
So if I want to find
these titles, I should
say, find me the titles where
the book_id is not equal to,
but is in this set of ids.
So let's try that.
Let me say SELECT "title"
FROM "books" WHERE
the "id" is IN some set of values--
is IN those two ids we saw earlier.
So I'll say IN, Enter--
1, 2, 3, 4, spaces.
And then I'll say SELECT the
"book_id" FROM "authored" WHERE--
let me actually space this again--
WHERE the "author_id" is equal
to the result of this subquery.
We can use equals here because there's
only one author_id we care about.
I'll hit Enter.
Then I'll do space,
space, space, space--
four spaces for one indentation--
and now four more spaces--
1, 2, 3, 4-- to indent again
to my next nested query.
I'll then say SELECT the "id"
FROM "authors" WHERE the "name"
is equal to 'Fernanda Melchor'.
And now let me close out my queries.
I'll hit Enter, space,
space, space, again.
And now I'll use parentheses to
close out my middle subquery.
I'll do the same.
I'll hit Enter.
And then I'll do another parentheses,
and then semicolon here, hit Enter.
And now I should see,
finally, Fernanda's two books.
So this is one example of using IN.
What questions do you have
on how to use this syntax?
SPEAKER: Actually, my
question was not regarding IN,
but actually the indentation
you use regarding the subqueries
because while you are
using the subqueries,
you mentioned that you
are giving four spaces.
Is there any necessity of using,
like, such kind of indentation
while we are using subqueries?
CARTER ZENKE: Yeah, a great
question about style here,
and let me try to pull up some slides
that have an example of that style
so we can talk about it.
Let me try to find an
example of our nested query.
I'll pull this one up.
And as you might remember,
we had three queries here.
And I tried to keep track of them by
indenting them more and more and more.
This isn't required.
You could-- I mean, don't do this.
But you could put it all on one line,
which would just be crazy long to read.
What we do instead is
we will often try to hit
Enter when it feels nice to have
a break in the reading length.
And we'll then indent some
spaces to show that this query is
a subquery of the prior one.
The exact amount to indent
might vary, but the idea
of trying to break up your
lines and trying to indent
is going to be a good one for your own
sake and for those who read your code.
Let's take one more too.
SPEAKER: When do we
need to use IN in WHERE
clause when we are doing subquerying?
I suppose that we can also use
subquerying without IN as well.
CARTER ZENKE: You're right.
So we saw an example using equals.
And we all saw an example using IN.
In general-- if you want just
a rule of thumb to follow--
if you're looking to see if some
id is part of a list of ids,
or part of a set of ids that is
more than one, you should use IN.
IN is good for checking if something
is inside of more than one item,
let's say.
Equals, though, is good if
you know you have only one id.
Let's say I have an id
equal to 23 or equal to 25.
That's a good place for equals.
If, though, I had 23 or
25, I might use IN to match
either/or of those in that set--
but good question.
And let's take one more here too.
SPEAKER: We have seen
one-to-many relationships,
one-to-one relationships, and
many-to-many relationships.
So how would many-to-one
relationships be tackled?
Suppose one book has three authors.
Then how would that be
represented in the tables?
CARTER ZENKE: Yeah, let's look
at the example of one book having
three authors, for instance.
And let's look at our authored table.
So let me pull up that
slide for you, and we'll
talk about it in just a minute.
I'll come back over here.
And I will pull up our example
of having authors, and books,
and the authored table in the middle.
And to your question of,
how could I have, let's say,
a book written by three authors?
Well, we could imagine that this table--
let's say, let's talk
about Boulder for instance.
So Boulder has the id of 1.
Let's say three people wrote Boulder.
Well, in this case,
we could adjust this.
I could say this is no longer 74.
This is 1.
And same thing here--
this is not 4; this is 1.
We have the book id 1
in here more than once.
It's in here 1, 2, 3 times.
But what we're saying each time is
that, well, 23 was an author of 1.
But 31 was an author of
1 as well, and so was 27.
So I would not be afraid
to have multiple instances
of your foreign key
inside of this table.
What I wouldn't do is have it more
than once in your primary key here.
Here it actually has some
information-- who authored which book.
Here it is strictly a
unique id that should
be only a one-to-one relationship.
Every key has to be unique
for the items in that table.
Good questions.
So we've seen subqueries.
But there is one more
technique we could use
to solve some of these problems
of querying across tables.
And this one is going
to be called a JOIN.
So let's dive into JOINs.
And the whole idea behind
JOIN is trying to take a table
and combine it with some other table.
And, actually, for this, we have some--
I don't know-- maybe some
guests for our class.
We have these very cute sea lions.
And we'll use a database of sea lions
to understand how JOINs actually work.
So if you're not familiar,
sea lions are sometimes
native to the coast of California.
And they like to travel.
They like to travel really far.
They go from the southern
part of California
all the way up to Washington State.
This is many, many miles of traveling
for these adorable sea lions.
So there are data sets that involve
sea lions and their migration patterns.
Here's one for example.
Here we have a table of sea lions.
And here we have a table
of their migrations.
A distance column tells us
how far they went in miles,
and a days column tells us how long
it took them to travel, of course,
in days.
Well, here, if we were
researchers, maybe
we're keeping track of
some number of sea lions.
We're keeping track of Ayah, and Spot,
and Tiger, Mabel, Rick, and Jolee.
But we have data on many
sea lions, perhaps some we
aren't even tracking anymore.
This would be our migrations table.
Now it could come to pass that
I want to figure out, well,
how far did Spot travel?
And how far did Tiger travel?
And what I could do is I could
use nested queries for this.
But perhaps, better yet, I
could try to join these tables
to see the data all in one table.
Now to do that, how can I try to take
a row from this side and kind of attach
it to or extend the row here?
What idea could I use to put the
right rows together in this case?
SPEAKER: Could you use
the primary key, the id,
to kind of join them together using
the prime key and the foreign key?
CARTER ZENKE: Yeah, a good idea.
So you might notice that we actually
have two columns here, both called
id, which is handy for us.
And notice how we have them kind of sort
of matching, and matching in the sense
that some of these ids are
actually inside of this column too.
So we could use the primary key
in literally both tables here,
and try to match it together to
figure out how these rows could
be extended to add more columns.
We could join these tables together
to make this table, ultimately,
showing us where Ayah has traveled and
how long it took them to get there.
So the keyword for doing these kinds
of manipulations with data in SQL
is called JOIN--
kind of straightforward.
But let's take a peek at what JOIN
can do for us inside of this database.
So I'll go to my computer here.
And I'll pull up this database of sea
lions that I prepared for us today.
I will clear up my terminal.
I'll type Control-L. And I'll
get out of my longlist database.
To do that, I can type dot
quit, a SQLite command,
to leave this environment.
I'll hit Enter.
And then what I can do is I can
type sqlite3 space sea_lions.db.
That is just the name of this database.
I'll hit Enter.
Now, let's make sure
I'm in the right place.
I could type dot tables to see what
tables are inside of this environment--
.tables, Enter.
I see both tables--
migrations and sea lions--
which is promising for me here.
So we could see what data
is inside of these tables.
I could say SELECT * FROM
"sea_lions"; hit Enter.
Now I see all of these adorable sea
lions inside of this lovely table.
What if I wanted to find migration?
So I could do that too.
I could say SELECT *
FROM "migrations"; Enter.
Now I see my data on migrations.
And notice how, again, some sea
lions are in the sea lions table.
And we have some ids
in our migrations table
that actually aren't
in our sea lions table.
So we're keeping track of
only a subset of sea lions.
And this data might have some sea lions
we kept track of in the past, so not
all of them as well.
So let's try joining these tables to
determine where have our sea lions been
in our sea lions table.
I'll say SELECT * FROM "sea_lions".
But now I don't want
to end this query here.
I want to expand this table with the
data inside of the migrations table.
So what could I do?
I'll hit Enter, just as a style
thing here, to now consider
how can we make a query a bit longer?
I'll want to JOIN the migrations
table to the sea lions table.
And to do that, I can type JOIN.
I'll say JOIN, then space.
And I want to say the
table I want to JOIN.
In this case, the table
is called migrations.
I'll say "migrations", and I
have to tell it one more thing.
I have to tell it what
we saw visually earlier,
which is that the id column in sea lions
matches the id column in migrations.
I have to tell SQL which two columns
to try to JOIN these tables by.
So let me do that.
I'll say JOIN "migrations" ON--
which is a SQL keyword--
what two columns should correspond?
I'll now say "migrations" dot "id"--
this means the id column
inside of migrations table--
is equal to, or is
going to be joined with,
this "sea_lions" table and
the "id" column within that.
Again, these two columns should
have some matching values
that we could use to make these
rows longer with more columns.
Let me then hit semicolon here.
And, hopefully, we'll see
all of our data now combined.
I can tell you how far Tiger
went, and how many days
it took them to do it because I've
joined these two tables together.
So in doing this kind of
JOIN, just a regular old JOIN,
what we're really doing is
part of this family of JOINs.
They're called an INNER JOIN.
You may have seen this idea of
an INNER JOIN or an OUTER JOIN.
The usual JOIN, at least in SQLite,
is going to be an INNER JOIN.
And what do we mean by INNER JOIN?
Well let's visualize it
a little more slowly here
and see the process of which we
might use to understand this JOIN.
I'll have, again, my two
tables but now simplified.
I have name and id, and
just distance and id.
And to JOIN these, I could literally
kind of nudge them together
and draw a line down the
middle, a bit like this.
But what do you notice?
This one seems to match this id.
And this id seems to match this id.
But these two-- well, they don't match.
I mean poor Jolee down here-- we
don't know how far Jolee went.
And if we don't know this data--
if these ids don't match--
is if we can not find a match
for this id or for this id,
well, let's sadly just
get rid of the row.
It's not part of our
joined table anymore.
It's gone from our memory.
We now have only these tables--
or these rows that we could
actually JOIN together
with the row and the other table here.
So, this is our example,
then, of an INNER JOIN.
Let me ask, what questions do
you have on these JOINs so far?
SPEAKER: So the confusion for me right
now is, where were the ids generated?
Was it on the sea lions table
or on the migrations table?
And what kind of problem can that
pose, like, maybe, in the real world?
So that's the question I have,
maybe not directly to JOINs itself.
CARTER ZENKE: No, that's a great
question and good to clarify.
So we have sea lions with some id.
And we see here that one id is 10484.
Another id is 11728.
And to your good question-- which
is, how do we get these ids--
well, these actually came to
us from researchers, perhaps,
who are researching sea lions.
And if you're not familiar,
let me go back to our slide
with sea lion migrations on it.
Researchers might often want to keep
track of where sea lions have been.
And to do so, they will
noninvasively apply some tag
to this animal that has
some unique id on it.
And they'll track where that tag goes
to understand where this particular sea
lion went.
So they will make up their
very own primary keys,
their very own unique ids,
to identify these sea lions.
We can then use those
same ids in our table
to understand where these
sea lions are going.
And just to be clear, too, let
me find our full data set here.
Here, we have those sea lions
that we're now interested in,
those we're now tracking.
But you could imagine that we also have
some sea lions that we no longer track,
and maybe they've gone on.
They're doing something else now.
They're not part of our data set.
So that's why we might see some
over here but not over here.
I hope that answers your question
about the sources of this data.
So let's take one more.
SPEAKER: When we join together
the two migration [INAUDIBLE]
the id definitely is repeating.
So I just want this and travel distance.
I don't want to repeat the table of id.
Is that possible?
CARTER ZENKE: Yeah, and I think--
if I'm understanding correctly-- we
want to try to not
just JOIN these tables,
but maybe remove the
duplicate id in them.
Like, if I showed you this JOINs table
right here, id appears in here twice.
There is a way to do this.
And we'll see it towards the
end of our exploration of JOINs.
We'll come back to
that in just a minute.
So we've seen INNER JOIN so far--
this way of combining tables and only
keeping the data that
actually matches between them.
But let's try a new way of joining.
This one that might not be so strict.
We have a few options here.
We have what we're going to call a LEFT
JOIN, a RIGHT JOIN, and a FULL JOIN.
And you could imagine, based on the
names here, what each one might do.
You could think of our tables--
one being on the left, one being on
the right, and trying to JOIN them,
prioritizing either the left
table or the right table
or maybe even both per a FULL JOIN.
So let's get a feel for
what kinds of tables
we get back from these
different commands.
And we'll talk about-- we'll visualize
how is this actually happening
underneath the hood.
Let's go back to our computer here.
And let's try to do a LEFT
JOIN using our two data sets.
Now a LEFT JOIN will prioritize, so to
speak, the data on my "left table"--
"left" being quote,
unquote, because there
is no left or right in a database.
But left here means the first
table that I start with.
So let's try this.
I'll say SELECT *--
and let me just make sure I'm
typing the right things here.
Let me try SELECT * FROM
the "sea_lions" table.
And now, I don't want to
just do a regular old JOIN.
I want to do a LEFT JOIN.
I want to, no matter what, always
have the data on my left table,
this sea lions table here--
LEFT JOIN.
And I'll JOIN "migrations".
I have to say the same thing.
Which column in "migrations" corresponds
to which column in "sea_lions"?
I'll say LEFT JOIN "migrations" ON
"migrations" dot "id" = "sea_lions"
dot "id" as well.
Now, I think that's just
about it for my JOIN.
So I'll say semicolon, Enter.
And notice the difference here.
Let me walk to this board so
we can see it in it's entirety.
I have all of my sea
lions now in this table.
Where we left off Jolee
earlier, we've now
kept Jolee in, even though Jolee doesn't
have a distance or a number of days.
We actually haven't tracked
that data yet for Jolee,
but we still see them in this table.
Let's now try a RIGHT JOIN to
see the difference between this
and the RIGHT JOIN.
I'll come back over here.
And let's try prioritizing
our rightmost table.
This one, perhaps, being
the migrations table.
So I'll say SELECT * FROM "sea_lions".
This will, again, be our left,
quote, unquote, table, just
because it comes first.
Now I'll say JOIN--
not just JOIN.
I'll say RIGHT JOIN
"migrations" ON, again,
"migrations" dot "id" =
"sea_lions" dot "id"; now let's
see the difference here.
Well, what have we done?
We've actually left off
a few sea lions now.
We only have those whose
ids were in the right table.
Again, the right table being
that second one we used.
And even if we don't have any
names for these sea lions,
we'll still include
them in our data set.
We can see, though, that this data
is missing and that, as we'll see,
it has some special value called null.
So we have a LEFT JOIN and a RIGHT JOIN.
A FULL JOIN, though, allows us to
see the entirety of both tables
and which values are missing.
Let's try that now.
I'll come back over here.
And I'll do a FULL JOIN.
I'll say SELECT * FROM "sea_lions" FULL
JOIN "migrations" ON "migrations"--
oh, "migrations" dot "id" is equal
to "sea_lions" dot "id"; Enter.
And now what do we see?
Well, we see both tables
in their entirety.
We have Jolee here still,
even though Jolee doesn't
have a distance or some number of days.
We also have our sea lions--
our mystery sea lions down
below-- who don't have any name but are
still included in our migration table
too.
So LEFT JOIN, FULL JOIN, and RIGHT JOIN.
So let's, then, visualize
this to understand
what's happening along the way.
I'll go back to some slides here.
And let's look first at
these LEFT JOINS as well.
So, really, all of these--
LEFT JOIN, RIGHT JOIN, and FULL JOIN--
these are all part of this
family called an OUTER JOIN.
An OUTER JOIN lets you keep some
data even if the JOIN is not
going to quite work out for you as much
as you would want it to in an INNER
JOIN.
By that, I mean you might have some
null or empty values in this JOIN
after you run it.
So let's visualize it.
Here I have a LEFT OUTER JOIN.
And I want to combine this left
table with this right table.
I'll do a LEFT OUTER JOIN.
I'll put them together.
And notice how these two don't match.
Well, because they don't match,
I'll fill in these values
with the value that
signifies empty or null.
In this case, it is, literally, null.
There's nothing here.
So because I did a LEFT JOIN,
what I should do is prioritize
this left table as data.
Even if this doesn't have any match
here, I'll still keep this row.
But notice down below that this
id has no match in the left table.
I'll omit that.
And in the end, I'll
delete this bottom row.
I'll be left with Jolee, who might or
may not have data in the right table.
Let's try the RIGHT JOIN--
RIGHT OUTER JOIN.
I'll do the same thing-- combine them.
And they'll do the same
exact kind of orientation.
I have some null values here that
I don't quite know how to match up.
What I can do instead
is say, well, I want
to prioritize the data
on this right-most table.
Even though this id has no
match, I want to keep it
because it's inside this right table.
OK, let me delete this row because
it has no match in my right table.
And I'll be back to this type of JOIN,
keeping every id in the right table.
A FULL JOIN, a bit more simple--
I'll take this same data, JOIN
it together, and I'll simply say,
I don't care if there
are no values involved.
I'll leave them be.
So this is a lot of visualizing.
Let me ask, what questions
do we have on these JOINs?
SPEAKER: Could I see how it
would work with multiple tables?
Is there, you know, if I have three
tables, which one is the left one?
Which one is the right one?
And what's the third one?
CARTER ZENKE: Yeah, good question.
So we've seen two tables so far.
And this was deliberate
kind of pedagogically
because it would be a lot to
see three JOINs all at once.
If you're thinking about
joining three tables, though,
and you're asking which one is your left
table, which one is your right table--
always it will be that the
table that comes first--
before your JOIN command, your
keyword, will be the left table.
And the table that's involved in your
JOIN keyword, like JOIN "migrations",
let's say, that will
be your right table.
And so you can imagine three
tables where for the first two,
the first one's on the left;
the first one's on the right.
For the next two, though,
the middle one's on the left
and the next one is on the right,
if that helps you visualize
without having much on the board here.
Good question.
Let's take one more.
SPEAKER: When we perform the JOIN
function, do we get under the hood?
Do we have, like, a
separate table that's
created which we can reference
later down in the code?
Or do we need to write that
entire JOIN command again?
CARTER ZENKE: Yeah, good question.
And so I believe you're asking,
do we get back a separate table
that we could use?
For this I might want
to doublecheck myself.
But just to kind of show you
what we've been doing so far,
I'll go back to my SQLite terminal here.
And I will ask, SELECT
* FROM "sea_lions",
and let's do a FULL JOIN with
"migrations" on "migrations"
dot "id" is equal to
"sea_lions" dot "id".
And I think what you're asking is, do we
get back a separate kind of table here?
We could consider it as
a kind of separate table.
If I hit Enter here,
this is kind of something
we're going to call a temporary table,
which you could also call a result set.
We can use this table for
the duration of our query.
What we haven't done,
though, is made this table
accessible in our database itself.
This is only there for the
duration of this query.
So, hopefully, that helps answer
it with a bit of fact-checking
if you need to as well.
OK, let's show one final type of JOIN
here, this one called a NATURAL JOIN.
A NATURAL JOIN kind of allows me to
omit the part of my previous JOINs
where I was saying "migrations"
dot "id" = "sea_lions" dot "id".
NATURAL JOIN says, both these
columns are called "id".
I could just assume that I want
you to JOIN by these two columns.
So let's try a NATURAL JOIN
and see what we get back.
I'll come back over here.
And we'll try a NATURAL JOIN
with our sea lions table
and our migrations table.
I'll say SELECT * FROM "sea_lions".
Then I'll NATURAL JOIN
"migrations" here.
And I no longer need to say "migrations"
dot "id" = "sea_lions" dot "id".
I can just hit semicolon,
and now I can hit Enter.
So we'll see that the JOIN
worked just as we wanted it to.
And we didn't even have to specify
which id column corresponded
to which other id column because these
were named the same column name id.
Notice, too, we don't get
a duplicate id column.
In some prior JOINs, we had an id
column here and an id column here.
Now, we've just combined
them into one single column,
or we've only kept one
column among this JOIN here.
So many kinds of JOINs to use.
Many ways to query our tables.
What we've seen so far is
how to organize our data,
build connections
between them, and now how
to query this data using
both subqueries and JOINS.
We'll take a quick
break here and come back
to see how we can use sets and groups
to, again, kind of refine our queries
and ask more interesting questions too.
Well, we're back.
And now we're going to focus
on this idea of sets in SQL.
So when you run a query,
you get back some results.
And those results are often called
a result set, some set of values
that you've gotten back from your table.
So let's take a look at
what sets are and how
we could use them to refine our
queries and to find relationships
among different groups of
people, places, or even things.
So let me ask a question of you.
Maybe in this world, we have authors
and we have translators, at least
in the publishing industry, right?
If you're in this set,
you are an author.
If you are in this set,
then you are a translator.
But what would it be, then,
if you were in this set?
What does this set mean?
SPEAKER: It means that
you are both the author
and the other one-- the translator.
CARTER ZENKE: Yeah, you're right.
So this means you are both
an author and a translator.
You're in the middle of these
two overlapping circles.
In SQL, we could represent
this kind of relationship
using our INTERSECT operator,
which we'll see in just a moment.
We'll take authors,
perhaps, and INTERSECT them
with those who are our
translators and find those
who are both authors and translators.
Let's do another one then.
Let's think of this set.
Who are you?
Or at least, what does this
set represent as a whole?
SPEAKER: It means that you're
either an author or a translator.
CARTER ZENKE: Nice.
You're either an author or a translator.
You could be both, too,
but you're in either camp.
You're either an author or a translator.
And for this, we could use
a SQL keyword called UNION.
I'll take my set of authors and
combine them with my set of translators
and get back, in this case,
the entirety of these two sets.
Let's look at this one too.
If you are in this set,
who is included there?
SPEAKER: Only authors will be included.
Authors which are also translators
are not being included here.
CARTER ZENKE: Yeah, good.
So here, only authors are included.
We see that those who are also
translators aren't included.
In fact, if you are an author and only
an author, then you are in this set.
And to get this kind of result, we
would use our SQL keyword called EXCEPT.
I'll take my set of authors
but subtract, or remove,
or EXCEPT my set of translators.
Similarly, I could say,
take my set of translators
and EXCEPT the set of authors--
subtract them, remove them.
And I could do that with
translators EXCEPT authors.
We'll see these keywords
in just a moment.
Now, I'll have one final question here,
which is, how could you represent this?
One, I mean, who are you if you
are in either this set or this set?
And how would you get that kind of set?
I actually saved that one
for you to do as homework,
if I may, before we move on to
seeing these in our actual terminal
environment.
So let's take this idea
of sets and apply it
to authors and translators,
this time in our database.
I'll come back over to
our SQLite terminal.
And let me now leave our
database of sea lions, sadly.
I'll type dot quit and go back
to my regular old terminal.
Now, I want to open back up
our longlist.db database--
longlist.db, hit Enter.
And now I'm back in the place
where I have authors, and books,
and publishers inside of this database.
I'll type Control-L
to clear my terminal.
And let's first try to find all of those
who are either translators or authors.
Well, what can I do?
I could try this.
Let me try SELECT--
SELECT "name" FROM "translators",
like this, from my translators table--
semicolon, Enter.
These are all of my translators.
Now, I want to find authors.
I could then say SELECT "name"
FROM "authors"; hit Enter.
Now I have all of my authors.
If I wanted, though, to
combine these results,
these results sets, I
could do so using UNION.
So let's try it.
I'll say SELECT "name"
FROM "translators"
and not finish my query yet.
I'll hit Enter, just for style's sake.
And I'll say UNION--
UNION with some other result I'll
get back from some separate query.
I'll hit Enter.
Now I'll say SELECT "name" FROM--
let's go for "authors" now, end
quote, semicolon, hit Enter.
And now I'll see both
authors and translators.
And we should see here that
every author and every translator
is in here only once.
We can assume that we have unique names
for these authors and translators.
And I could scroll through and
figure out who is either an author
or a translator-- actually
see them both in the same set.
If I wanted, I could distinguish
between "authors" and "translators"
by adjusting my query just a little bit.
I could say SELECT--
let's go for SELECT 'author',
the string, AS "profession"
and also select "name" FROM
the author's table, semicolon.
This would give me back not
just one column of names,
but also another column
called profession
that has just author inside
of it I'll hit Enter.
And I'll see I, indeed,
have this column--
if I scroll all the way
up-- called profession.
And I have the value being author.
Let's combine these.
Let's UNION this set with
the set of translators
and give them their profession too.
I'll say SELECT
"authors" AS "profession"
and then, also, "name"
FROM the authors table.
And now I'll hit Enter.
And I'll say UNION that set
with the set of translators.
I'll say SELECT 'translator', the
string, AS the column "profession".
Then I'll say "name"
FROM the "translators"--
"name" FROM the "translators" table,
quote, unquote, semicolon, hit Enter.
And now I could actually see who is
a translator and who is an author.
If I scroll through here,
I'll see translators.
And now, I'll also see authors.
So I've combined these two sets
into one that works for me here.
So this is how to UNION,
or combine, our sets.
But what if we wanted to find only
those who are authors and translators,
kind of a unique niche group of folks.
But who is part of this set?
Well, let's try to find out.
I could SELECT "names" FROM the
"authors" table, as I did before.
Now, instead of UNION, let me
INTERSECT these names with those
that will be in the translators column.
I'll say INTERSECT and SELECT
"name" FROM "translators".
And now I'll hit semicolon, Enter.
And I'll see one.
His name is Ngugi, who is both
an author and a translator.
They translated their
own book into English
for the International Booker Prize.
So let's try now to find those
who aren't just translators
and authors, but only those
who are, perhaps, translators,
or only those who are authors.
So let's try this.
I'll say SELECT "name"
FROM "authors", hit Enter.
And now I want to EXCLUDE
those who are also translators.
I'll say EXCEPT, in
this case, SELECT "name"
FROM "translators", hit semicolon.
And now I should see-- if I
pay close enough attention--
that Ngugi is not in this list.
They are an author, and they
were in the author set of names.
But because they're also a translator,
they're not inside this set of list.
So this is finding--
good for finding who
is in one list, who is in some other
list, and who is in-between them.
But it's also nice for trying to find
books people have collaborated on,
let's say.
Maybe I want to find the books that
both Sophie Hughes and Margaret
Costa have written together, jointly.
So I could try to find, first, the
books that Sophie Hughes has translated.
Let's say SELECT "book_id"
FROM the "translated" table--
this table that has translated-- which
has translators and books inside of it.
And then I'll say WHERE
the "translator_id" is
equal to this subquery.
I'll find Sophie Hughes's
id as a translator.
I'll say SELECT "id" FROM
"translators" WHERE the "name"
is 'Sophie Hughes', semicolon to end.
And these are the book ids that
Sophie Hughes has translated
because Sophie Hughes is a translator.
Well, let's see, maybe
they have translated
some books with Margaret Costa as well.
I could try to find out.
I'll say SELECT "book_id"--
we'll try to find Sophie's books again.
I'll say SELECT "book_id"
FROM "translated"
WHERE the "translator_id"
is equal to, again,
Sophie Hughes's "translator_id"--
SELECT "id" FROM "translators" WHERE
the "name" is 'Sophie Hughes' like this.
Now, I'll close out
this part of my query.
But I want to find the
intersection-- the set of book ids
that are the same between
Sophie Hughes's translated works
and Margaret Costa's
translated works too.
So I'll continue.
I'll say INTERSECT this result with
some other query I'll write now.
Let me SELECT the "book_id"
FROM the "translated"
table WHERE the "translator_id" is
equal to a different kind of query.
This one will get back
the id for Margaret Costa.
I'll say SELECT "id" from "translators"
WHERE the "name" is equal to--
and I believe in this particular case,
they go by 'Margaret Jull Costa', like
this.
Now I'll hit Enter,
close out this subquery,
and finally, I can hit semicolon.
This is the end of my query--
semicolon here.
And now I'll see the book_id
they have collaborated on.
You could imagine going beyond this to
find the title of this book_id using
another nested query.
But I won't spend time on
that, at least for now,
because I'd have to write all
this text back out for you.
So we've seen UNION. .
We've seen EXCEPT.
We've seen INTERSECT.
What questions do you have on
these sets and how they work?
SPEAKER: You've got three JOINs.
I just wondered if there
was a default that you
chose if you didn't know what the
situation was, like, which one to use?
CARTER ZENKE: Yeah, so we
saw different kinds of JOINs.
We saw LEFT JOIN, RIGHT JOIN, FULL JOIN.
And the default, as we saw a
little before, is just the simple.
JOIN and that JOIN is an
example of an INNER JOIN.
It'll only take those rows
where the ids actually match up.
You could get more specific and have
a LEFT or a RIGHT JOIN or a FULL JOIN.
But we'll leave that for
you to try out on your own
and see the results of, as we did
before too, but great question.
SPEAKER: You mentioned that
the ids from both tables
were used to match the two
tables and we didn't have
to whatever duplicate column from id.
So I was wondering, in a situation
whereby the primary key, actually,
like, for instance, let's say you're
trying to JOIN [? return ?] that table,
[? where ?] [? your ?] [INAUDIBLE]
is [INAUDIBLE] like a foreign key,
how would you go about doing that?
Because it seems we
didn't specify the ids
where we wanted to make the
JOINs on with the NATURAL JOIN.
So I just needed some
clarification on that front.
CARTER ZENKE: Yeah, and let me make
sure I'm understanding correctly.
So I think you're trying
to think about how
you would JOIN a table that
has a different kind of column
name from the other one.
And for that, you could
use the equals there.
And you could say--
we said "migrations" dot
"id" = "sea_lions" dot "id".
But let's say the sea lions id was
actually called sea lion underscore id,
like the full thing spelled out--
I could say JOIN
"migrations" ON "migrations"
dot "id" equals "sea_lions"
dot "sealions_id" to spell out
the column name for SQL.
Good question, too.
SPEAKER: Can I use the INTERSECT and
the UNION together between more than two
tables, three tables, or four tables?
CARTER ZENKE: Yeah, you could
use intersect more than once,
let's say, to intersect
more than one set.
You absolutely could.
And here-- I don't have a
good example planned for this.
But you could have one query that
does one thing-- give you some set.
And you type INTERSECT after it.
Then you get back the next query.
And you find the intersection of that.
You could then type INTERSECT
again to get the intersection
of all of these three sets.
You can keep going,
going, as you'd like to.
The key thing here, though, is that
in your INTERSECTs, or in your UNIONs,
or in your EXCEPT, you always
have to have the same number
and the same type of columns.
So if I was trying to combine, let's
say, author names with book titles,
I can't INTERSECT or UNION
those quite well because they
have different kind of meanings.
They're different kinds of things.
So if you're trying to JOIN multiple
thing-- trying to JOIN multiple tables
or INTERSECT multiple
tables, make sure you always
have those same column names
and those same column types--
the type of data that's stored inside.
So we've seen sets now.
And we're going to conclude by
looking at this idea of groups.
Well, groups will allow
us to recreate some
of what we tried to do a
little bit of last week,
trying to understand the
average rating of some books.
So let's take a look at groups now.
Well, you could imagine that
I have my ratings table.
And in this ratings
table, I have book_ids.
And I also have ratings.
Here, I see that the book-id
of 1 has several ratings
from people who gave the book a rating.
It has 4, 3, and 4.
And similarly, book-id with 2
has two ratings from folks--
2 and 3.
Now, I want to find the average rating
across these ratings for each book_id.
So let me try that in my terminal.
Come back over here
and let me, first, try
to find the average rating
for each of these books.
So I'll go back.
And I'll say, why don't I SELECT average
"rating" FROM my "ratings" table.
And I think this should be good
enough, so I'll hit semicolon.
And I'll see, well, 3.83644.
And this seems to be an average.
But I wanted the average of each book.
So what did I do wrong here?
What am I actually seeing in this case?
SPEAKER: Isn't it an average of
all books in the entire table?
CARTER ZENKE: Yeah, good instinct.
So let me try to put
back our table here,
and we can see what's actually going on.
I'll come back over here.
And I will show us, again, this table.
So we had a table of ratings.
And we had the rating column that
has individual ratings inside of it.
When I say SELECT the average
rating from this table, well,
what am I getting?
I'm getting the average of all of
these ratings not grouped by book_id.
So if I want to find the
average rating for each book,
I need to employ this idea of groups.
And, I mean, wouldn't it be nice
if I could do something like this?
I could kind of highlight the
rows that are part of each group,
and then try to average those.
I could say, take all the books with
id 1 and all the books with id 2
and just collapse their
ratings, like this.
And once you do that,
find the average for me,
and give me that back as a table.
That would be kind of nice.
And, luckily, we actually have
the capacity to do that with SQL
using this GROUP BY keyword.
So we'll see this in action.
I'll come back over here.
And let's try to redo this
query to find the right answer.
I'll come back.
And I'll say let's SELECT, in
this case, the book_ids and also
their average rating.
I'll SELECT "book_id".
that's one column I want.
And I also want the average rating
from this column, from this table.
Now I'll say, let me title this,
perhaps, AS "average rating".
So I'll get the average rating and
just title that column "average rating"
exactly.
I want to SELECT this
FROM the "ratings" table.
But now, I don't want
to simply hit Enter.
I'll get back the same
thing I did before,
which is the average of all the
ratings in the ratings table.
What I want is for these ratings--
the average ratings-- to
be grouped by the book_id.
So I'll say GROUP BY
"book_id"; hit Enter.
And now I should be able to
see the results I wanted.
Let me scroll to the top and
notice how using GROUP BY,
I was able to take each
book_id, collapse the rows--
the ratings that were
associated with this book--
and find the average of that rating--
3.77, 3.97, 3.04-- for each
book, so kind of handy here.
Let me try to improve this and
show you one additional thing
we could do as well.
I'll come back.
And why don't I try to
replicate what we did
last time, which was find the books
that have a certain rating or higher.
Let's try that.
I'll say SELECT the "book_id".
And let's get, now, the rounded rating--
the rounded average rating.
I'll ROUND the average
"rating" to two decimal places.
And I'll call this "average
rating" as a column.
I'm going to SELECT this
FROM my "books" table--
FROM my "ratings" table, sorry.
And now I want to GROUP
BY the "book_id" to find
the average rating for each "book_id".
Now, though, let's say I only want
those books that are pretty well rated,
greater than 4.0 out of 5.0 stars.
To include a WHERE clause, I could
try following up on this GROUP BY.
And you might think, I could
say, well, WHERE the average--
WHERE "average rating"--
that new column I created--
is greater than or equal to 4.0.
But I can't because these
are now not individual rows.
They are groups.
SQL uses a different keyword
for conditions on groups
than for conditions on individual rows.
And this keyword is called HAVING--
H-A-V-I-N-G. Let me try that--
H-A-V-I-N-G. I want to
GROUP BY the "book_id"
and only keep those that have an
average rating of greater than 4.0.
I will scroll over here,
and I'll hit Enter.
And now I should see
a much smaller list.
I see "book_id" 5 has a 4.06.
10 has a 4.04, and so on.
And now the next step is--
you can imagine me, perhaps,
joining these book_ids with another
table that has titles inside of it,
too, to find the average rating
given some title as well.
So GROUPs allow us to take these
columns, collapse some rows,
and find aggregate statistics
across each of those GROUPs.
Let me ask, then, what
questions do we have on GROUPs?
SPEAKER: What if I don't want to
see the average rating of a book,
but how many ratings does it have?
CARTER ZENKE: Oh, a good one.
So I want to know not the average
rating, but the number of reviews,
let's say, the number of ratings
it was given in my table.
Well, for that, I could just
modify my query a little bit.
I could change average to COUNT because
COUNT counts up the number of rows
that I have.
So let me try that here.
I'll come back to my laptop.
And let me try this one
I will SELECT "book_id",
and I will also SELECT the
COUNT of "book_id" in my-- no,
I'll also select the COUNT of "ratings,"
we're gonna say how many ratings there
are-- inside my ratings table--
COUNT("rating") FROM let's say
the "ratings" table, like this.
Now I want to GROUP this data--
GROUP the counting by book_id.
So I'll say Group By "book_id"--
give me a count of the
ratings for each book_id.
And now, I could just
hit semicolon and Enter.
And now, I'll see how many
ratings each book actually has.
Let me go to the top here.
And I'll see book id
1 has 2,779 ratings.
Book_id 2 has 176 ratings, and so on--
a good question.
Let's take one more too.
SPEAKER: So considering these
new having syntax, how could we
couple that with the ORDER BY?
CARTER ZENKE: Yeah, where
does it fit in with ORDER BY?
Like, let's say I want to sort this
data, too, at the end of the day.
Well, I could do that as well.
Let me show you one example.
I'll come back to my terminal.
And I could try this.
Let me come back to find
the average ratings.
So I'll say SELECT "book_id"
and the rounded average rating
to two decimal places, calling
that column "average rating".
And I'll SELECT this
FROM the "ratings" table.
Well, now, we want not just
to find the average rating.
We also want to SORT by that column too.
And in fact, use HAVING to only find
those books that have 4.0 or higher.
Well, let's try this.
I'll say FROM "ratings", and
I'll still GROUP BY "book_id".
Now, I'll say I only want to
filter to those groups that have
a "average rating" of greater than 4.0.
And finally, after I've filtered out
all of these rows, I want to order them.
I want to sort them.
So I'll order them by "average
rating", this column I made up top.
And I'll say order them
in descending order.
I want biggest to smallest.
And fingers crossed-- I'll hit Enter,
and we'll see our ratings sorted
for us--
so great question here to re-implement
much of what we did last time.
And now, indeed, we've kind
of come full circle here.
We've taken these ideas, and
we've seen them in single tables,
as we did last week.
We-- this week, took our tables, and
expanded them into multiple tables--
different authors, different publishers,
different ratings, and so on.
And we learned how to query those
tables using subqueries and using JOINs.
What we'll see next time is
putting you in the driver's seat,
having you actually create your own
tables, define your own relationships,
and build a database to your own
liking, so all that and more next time.
We'll see you there.