[MUSIC PLAYING]
DAVID J. MALAN: Hello, world.
This is CS50's Introduction to Databases with SQL, or Sequel.
My name is David Malan.
CARTER ZENKE: And my name is Carter Zenke.
DAVID J. MALAN: CS50 itself is an introduction to computer science.
And along the way you learn about SQL and more.
This course dives all the more deeply into SQL specifically.
And you can take it before, during, or after CS50 itself,
whether you're a computer scientist, data scientist, programmer, or simply
someone who's interested in databases.
CARTER ZENKE: Now we'll begin with software
called SQLite, which you can use to query a table of data,
maybe a table of books, for instance.
You will then graduate and work not just with one table but multiple,
and see how to define relationships among them.
Afterwards you'll figure out how to design your very
own database from scratch, learning about schemas and data types.
And then you'll see how to add data to that database,
how to insert, update, and delete some data altogether.
Soon after you'll see how to write alternate views
for your data, new ways of simplifying your data for yourself and for others.
And then, towards the end of the course, you
will see how to optimize your queries, how to reduce the time that they take,
although at the cost of some space.
And then finally, to cap it all off, you'll
learn other DBMSs, Database Management Systems, like MySQL and Postgres,
that you can use to do all of this and more at a much bigger scale.
Now this is CS50.